<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Consultancy Services | John Mburu</title>
    <link>https://mburu.netlify.app/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://mburu.netlify.app/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Consultancy Services</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 05 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://mburu.netlify.app/media/icon_hu1f071ece8f91d52fd6c349e21cb6fa83_73823_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Consultancy Services</title>
      <link>https://mburu.netlify.app/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data Analysis and Management</title>
      <link>https://mburu.netlify.app/project/services/dataanalysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mburu.netlify.app/project/services/dataanalysis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I provide comprehensive training for organizations and individuals in statistical analysis and data management using Stata, R, and SPSS. These powerful tools enable users to perform advanced data analysis, create detailed reports, and make data-driven decisions. My training programs are designed to cater to all skill levels, from beginners to advanced users, ensuring that participants gain a solid understanding of each software&amp;rsquo;s functionalities and applications. Through hands-on sessions and practical exercises, I equip participants with the skills needed to effectively manage and analyze data, ultimately enhancing their research capabilities and decision-making processes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data Management System</title>
      <link>https://mburu.netlify.app/project/services/datamanagementsystems/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mburu.netlify.app/project/services/datamanagementsystems/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I work with organization to support their learning journey. I am committed to supporting organizations in the development of robust Monitoring, Evaluation, and Learning (MEL) systems - including theories of change, learning agendas, and data collection, storage, and analysis systems. To complement these efforts, I assist in designing intuitive dashboards that facilitate real-time data visualization and analysis, empowering organizations to make informed decisions and demonstrate their impact to stakeholders.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ecomonic Modelling</title>
      <link>https://mburu.netlify.app/project/services/economicsmodelling/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mburu.netlify.app/project/services/economicsmodelling/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I offer specialized training for organizations and individuals in computable general equilibrium (CGE) modeling and economic modeling. These advanced techniques are crucial for analyzing the impacts of economic policies, shocks, and structural changes on an economy. My training programs are tailored to meet the needs of participants at various levels of expertise, providing a solid foundation in the theoretical underpinnings as well as practical applications of CGE and economic modeling. Through interactive sessions and real-world case studies, I ensure that participants develop the necessary skills to construct, calibrate, and interpret complex economic models, enabling them to make informed decisions and contribute to policy analysis and economic planning effectively.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
